In this video, I'd like to start to talk about clustering.
在这个视频中 我将开始介绍聚类算法
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
This will be exciting because this
这将是一个激动人心的时刻
is our first unsupervised learning algorithm
因为这是我们学习的第一个非监督学习算法
where we learn from unlabeled data
我们将要让计算机学习无标签数据
instead of the label data.
而不是此前的标签数据
So, what is unsupervised learning?
那么 什么是非监督学习呢
I briefly talked about unsupervised
在课程的一开始
learning at the beginning of
我曾简单的介绍过非监督学习
the class but it's useful
然而 我们还是有必要
to contrast it with supervised learning. So, here's
将其与监督学习做一下比较
a typical supervisory problem where
在一个典型的监督学习中
we are given a label training sets
我们有一个有标签的训练集
and the goal is to find
我们的目标是找到
the decision boundary that separates the
能够区分正样本和负样本的
positive label examples and the negative label examples.
决策边界
The supervised learning problem in
在这里的监督学习中
this case is given a
我们有一系列标签
set of labels to fit a hypothesis to it.
我们需要据此拟合一个假设函数
In contrast, in the unsupervised
与此不同的是
learning problem, we're given
在非监督学习中
data that does not have
我们的数据没有
any labels associated with it.
附带任何标签
So we're given data that looks
我们拿到的数据就是这样的
like this, here's a set
在这里
of points and then no labels.
我们有一系列点 却没有标签
And so our training set is written
因此 我们的训练集可以写成
just x1, x2 and
只有x(1) x(2)
so on up to x(m)
一直到 x(m)
and we don't get any labels y.
我们没有任何标签y
And that's why the points plotted
因此 图上画的这些点
up on the figure don't have
没有
any labels on them.
标签信息
So in unsupervised learning, what
也就是说 在非监督学习中
we do is, we give this sort of
我们需要将一系列
unlabeled training set to
无标签的训练数据
an algorithm and we just
输入到一个算法中
ask the algorithm: find some
然后我们告诉这个算法
structure in the data for us.
快去为我们找找这个数据的内在结构
Given this data set, one
给定数据
type of structure we might
我们可能需要某种算法
have an algorithm find, is that
帮助我们寻找一种结构
it looks like this data set has
图上的数据看起来
points grouped into two
可以分成两个
separate clusters and so
分开的点集（称为簇）
an algorithm that finds that
一个能够找到
clusters like the ones I just
我圈出的这些点集的算法
circled, is called a clustering
就被称为
algorithm.
聚类算法
And this will be our first type of
这将是我们介绍的
unsupervised learning, although there
第一个非监督学习算法
will be other types of unsupervised
当然 此后我们还将提到
learning algorithms that we'll talk
其他类型的非监督学习算法
about later that finds other
它们可以为我们
types of structure or other
找到其他类型的结构
types of patterns in the data other than clusters.
或者其他的一些模式 而不只是簇
We'll talk about this afterwards, we will talk about clustering.
我们将先介绍聚类算法 此后 我们将陆续介绍其他算法
So what is clustering good for?
好啦 那么聚类算法一般用来做什么呢？
Early in this class I had already mentioned a few applications.
在这门课程的早些时候 我曾经列举过一些应用
One is market segmentation, where
比如市场分割
you may have a database of
也许你在数据库中
customers and want to group
存储了许多客户的信息
them into different market segments.
而你希望将他们分成不同的客户群
So, you can sell to
这样你可以对不同类型的客户分别销售产品
them separately or serve your different market segments better.
或者分别提供更适合的服务
Social network analysis, there are
社交网络分析
actually, you know, groups that have done
事实上 有许多研究人员
this, things like looking at a
正在研究这样一些内容
group of people, social networks,
他们关注一群人 关注社交网络
so things like Facebook, Google plus
例如 Facebook Google+
or maybe information about who
或者是其他的一些信息
are the people that you
比如说
email the most frequently and who
你经常跟哪些人联系
are the people that they email
而这些人
the most frequently, and
又经常给哪些人发邮件
to find coherent groups of people.
由此找到关系密切的人群
So, this would be another maybe
因此 这可能需要另一个
clustering algorithm where, you know, you'd want
聚类算法
to find who other coherent groups of friends in a social network.
你希望用它发现社交网络中关系密切的朋友
Here's something that one of my
我有一个朋友
friends actually worked on, which is,
正在研究这个问题
use clustering to organize compute
他希望使用聚类算法
clusters or to organize data
来更好的组织计算机集群
centers better because, if you
或者更好的管理数据中心
know which computers in the
因为如果你知道数据中心中
data center are in the cluster there tend to work together.
那些计算机经常协作工作
You can use that to reorganize
那么 你可以
your resources and how you
重新分配资源
lay out its network and
重新布局网络
how design your data center and communications.
由此优化数据中心 优化数据通信
And lastly something that, actually
最后 我实际上
another thing I worked on, using
还在研究
clustering algorithms to understand
如何利用聚类算法
galaxy formation and using
了解星系的形成
that to understand how, to
然后用这个知识
understand astronomical detail.
了解一些天文学上的细节问题
So, that's clustering which
好的 这就是聚类算法
is our first example of
这将是我们介绍的第一个
an unsupervised learning algorithm.
非监督学习算法
In the next video, we'll start to
在下一个视频中 我们将开始介绍
talk about a specific clustering algorithm.
一个具体的聚类算法